So in the last lecture we created this new project structure,
Dolaysyla son konferansta bu yeni proje yapsna borluyuz.
let's now start filling the cockpit and persons.js file with some life.
imdi kokpite doldurmaya balayalm ve ahsi sandalyeler biraz mr tkeniyor.
I'll start with persons and persons can also be a functional component because I don't need to manage
Ben balayacam kiiler ve kiiler ilevsel bir bileen olabilir, nk burada devleti ynetmek
state in there.
zorunda deilim.
So what I will do is I will again create a constant, persons, which is just a function in the end, a function
Bu yzden, ne yapacam, Tekrar End Function'n bir fonksiyonu olan srekli varl yaratacam.
that will receive props though.
Babam olsa sahne alacak.
Now here is the another way we can write this function body though.
imdi, yazabileceiniz say biimi ilev gvdesi olsa ite burada.
Thus far, we always simply return something there,
imdiye dek orada her zaman sadece bir eyler dndryoruz.
now we can definitely do that.
imdi bunu kesinlikle yapabiliriz.
But if we only want to return something in that function body due to our project set up and all the ES6 features
Fakat biz sadece bu fonksiyon cesedindeki Ju-Ju'ya bir eyler iade etmek istersek, projemizde ve alt
we can use
zellii kullanabiliriz.
or the next gen features in general, we can use we can shorten this to just return parentheses.
Veya genelde kullanabileceimiz yeni zellikler, parantezleri geri getirmek iin ksaltabiliriz.
Now this is simply due to the way arrow functions work,
imdi bu sadece aero ilevlerinin almas gereidir.
if you write them in one line and this by way does not mean that you can't split the path inside the parentheses
Onlar tek bir satr halinde yazarsanz bu, parantez iindeki paray birden ok satra blebileceiniz
across multiple lines
anlamna gelmez.
but you start with that in the same line.
Ama ayn satrda balyorsunuz.
If you only have that one line and not multiple lines as a function body, you can simply start with the
Tek bir satrnz varsa ve birden fazla satr bir ilev gvdesi olarak kullanmyorsanz, return deyimiyle
return statement and if you return parentheses, this is what we got here
balayabilirsiniz ve parantez iine dnerseniz buraya burada varolduumuz ey budur.
since you omit the return statement in this one line notation.
Bu tek satrlk gsterimde return deyimini atladnz iin.
So that's the default ES6 arrow function notation,
Yani varsaylan E-6 ok fonksiyonu gsterimi.
if it's in one line, this automatically gets returned and you can hence omit the return statement.
Bir satrdaysa bu otomatik olarak geri dner ve bylece u dn bildirimini atlarsnz.
Now in here, you directly put your jsx
imdi her yerde seimi dorudan koyarsn.
code.
Evet X kodu.
Now this is not everything,
imdi bu her ey deil.
we of course also have to import react as before
Tabii ki daha nce olduu gibi tepki vermeliyiz.
and now we know that props will contain an array of persons which we want to transform into an array
imdi de pervane, evet yaptmz gibi Js elemanlar dizisine dntrmek
of jsx elements just as we did in app.js
istediimiz bir dizi kii ieriyor biliyoruz.
So we can basically copy the code from there, the persons map code here where we map our array into an array
Bylece temel olarak burada kiilerin harita kodunu kopyalayabiliriz burada dizimizi bir dizi kiiye
of persons, I'll copy this code,
kopyaladmz bu kodun tamam kopyalanr.
we still will need to adjust it though
Yine de ayarlamamz gerekecek.
but this will be relatively easy. So in persons.js
Ancak bu ahsen daha kolay olacak.
here inside my parentheses,
J. S. Burada parantezlerimde.
I will call persons map though on the props, props.persons.map
Pervane'nin mucizevi haritasnda olsa da, Pearse'n haritasn arayacam.
And now here keep in mind, we're already writing jsx. So we can even omit the parentheses here because
Ve imdi unu unutmayn ki zaten J'yi GSX olarak yazyoruz, burada parantezleri atlayabiliriz nk
we're not having a jsx expression here,
burada bir gs x ifadesine sahip deiliz.
this this normal javascript after all, it will contain jsx in the inside
Bu normal javascript yapar Sonuta J'yi J ve X olarak ieriyor olacak.
but that doesn't change the fact that props.persons.map is normal javascript code we're calling.
Fakat bu mreffeh haritann normal javascript kodunun geri arld gereini deitirmez.
So with that, we're now returning person here and we need to import that person component, so import person
Dolaysyla artk burada kiiyi geri getiriyoruz ve o kii bileenini ie aktarmamz gerekiyor, bu
from ./Person/Person pointing to the person.js file.
nedenle kiiyi noktal eik izgi kisinden kiiyi js dosyasna gsteren kiiden ie aktarn.
With that, we get a very short and concise way of writing this,
Bununla bunu yazmann ok ksa ve zl bir yolunu buluyoruz.
We got our persons which we expect to receive on our props and that we still map persons, this array into
Sahnelerimizden almay umduumuz ve hala kiilerin desirliini bir dizi GSX unsuru haline
an array of jsx elements.
getirdiimiz iin nedenlerimiz var.
Now one thing we still need to do is we need to adjust our clicked and changed handler because this
imdi hl yapmamz gereken bir ey, tklama ve deitirme ileyicimizi ayarlamamz gerektii iin, kii ileyicisini
deletePersonHandler and this nameChangedHandler,
sil ve bu ad ileyiciyi deitirdi.
that won't work anymore because we no longer have these methods here,
Artk bu ie yaramayacak nk artk bu yntemleri burada yok.
we no longer have a class here
Artk burada bir snfmz yok.
this is just a function. Of course you could create a class here and handle the deletions on here
Elbette burada bir snf oluturup burada silme ilemlerini gerekletirebileceiniz bir ilevdir.
but keep in mind that this should typically be handled in a couple of or very few containers and not
birka veya ok az sayda konteynrda ele alnmas gerektiini ve tm bileenlerinizin iinde ele alnmamas gerektiini unutmayn.
in all your components.
Ancak bunun tipik olarak
So the way to handle this would be to not call this but props.deletePersonHandler
Bu iin ekli, bunu aramamak ama belki lider kii ileyicisidir.
and props, though again not deletePersonHandler but more likely the name of the property we want to
Belki de olsa, kii ileyicisi deil, daha olaslkla biz kullanmak istediimiz mlkn
use
ad.
Like props.clicked and maybe props.changed. With these changes in place, let's export our persons function
Sanki pervane toplanyor ve belki de bu deiikliklerle pervane deiti, hapishanelerimizi burada ihra
here,
edelim.
so export default persons and make sure to save all files.
Varsaylan kiileri da aktarn ve tm dosyalar kaydettiinizden emin olun.
Now let's go back to the app.js file, there we no longer need this code of course,
imdi getiimiz sonbaharda uygulamaya geri dnelim, elbette bu kodu artk istemiyoruz.
instead what we do need here is we simply need to reach out to our persons component.
Bunun yerine, her yl yaptmz ey, yalnzca kiilerin bileenine ulamaktr.
So let's add this import, import persons from Persons/Persons,
Bu ithalat ithalat kisilerini kisilere indirgeyelim.
this is our new import path pointing to the persons.js file in the persons folder.
Bu, kiiler klasrndeki kiinin js dosyasna iaret eden yeni alma yolumuzdur.
With that we can use persons like this here
Bununla bu ylki insanlar kullanabiliriz.
and now, we need to pass three pieces of information to that component, the three props we're using, the
Ve imdi, o bileene D3 cretsiz pervanenin  parasn iletmek zorundayz ki,
persons prop, the click prop and the change prop,
kiinin Propp'u tklama istemini ve deiiklik istemini kullanyoruz.
these are the three props we're accessing. Person, name, age and key,
Bunlar, Persse isim ana ve anahtarna erimekte olduumuz cretsiz sahne rnleridir.
that doesn't really matter because that is the individual person from that persons array we are looping
yok, nk bu kiilerin dolaabildikleri tek kii.
through
Gerekten nemi
so we only need props persons, clicked and changed. Back in app.js, we should parse that persons
Bu yzden yalnzca pervanelerin kiileri tklatt ve geri dnd ve aslnda evet, bu
simply is this.state.persons, let me
kiileri terketmek zorunda kaldk, o kiileri terk etmeliydik.
split these over multiple lines to make it easier to read, clicked should pass a reference to the function you want
Ancak okumay kolaylatrmak iin yalanlar sonucunda toplama, kullancnn bileeninden atldnda yrtmek istediiniz
to execute when this is fired from the persons component.
yaz tipine bir referans iletmelidir.
So here this will be this.deletePersonHandler and changed, that will be this.nameChangedHandler,
Yani ite bu kii silenecek ileyici olacak ve deitirilen veriler bu ileyici deitirilmi olacak.
now let's see if that works as it should.
Bakalm gerektii gibi alp almadn grelim.
We can now remove that old code down there,
imdi orada ldrlen olunu kaldrabiliriz.
all we have here is our persons component which will render the list and we still conditionally show
Burada sahip olduumuz, listeyi oluturacak olan kiinin bileeni olup, koullu
it or don't show it.
olarak gsterebilir veya gstermeyiz.
Make sure all files are saved
Tm dosyalarn kaydedildiinden emin olun.
and let's reload our application, make sure npm start is still running and toggle the persons,
Ve uygulamanz tekrar ykleyelim, UM balatma ileminin hala altndan ve kiilerle konutuundan emin olalm.
it does looks pretty good,
Olduka iyi grnyor.
we can still work with it as we did before but now if we use the react developer tools and dive into
Daha nce alm olduumuz gibi yine de birlikte alabiliriz ancak imdi tekrar hareket eden
that, you'll see we did get our persons component here with our individual person or if we reload of course
gelitirici aralarn kullanp dala devam edersek, antalarmz burada bireysel kiimizle birlikte alm olduumuzu greceksiniz ya da
with all our persons, these three.
tabii tm hapishanelerimizle yeniden yklersek bunlar cretsiz.
So it's working as before
Yani daha nce olduu gibi alyor.
but we improved the structure a little bit because now in the app container, we don't have to worry about
Ancak yapy biraz gelitirdik nk imdi uygulama kapsaycsnda bu listenin oluturulma mant
the logic of creating that list,
hakknda endielenmene gerek yok.
We outsource this to the persons.js file and it is the best practice to create regular pieces where
Bunu kiinin satran dosyasna yapyoruz ve her bileenin net bir oda olduu
each component has a clear focus.
dzenli paralar oluturmak en iyi yntemdir.
Now the same goes for the cockpit, there
imdi orada ayn kokpite de gidiyor.
we also want to outsource the logic to the cockpit.js file
Ayrca, mant kokpite J.'den da aktarmak istiyoruz. S. dosya.
and for the cockpit, we basically need to put the h1 tag, the paragraph and the button into its own component.
girerek yapabiliriz Ve ynetmek zorunda kalmadmz iin bu da fonksiyonel bir bileen olacak kendi devleti.
So we can simply do that by going into the cockpit.js file and there again, this will be a functional
Ve kokpit iin temelde ya tek bir teknolojik paragrafa ve batonun kendi bileenine
component because it doesn't need to manage its own state,
koymamz gerekiyor, bylece bunu kokpite Jaspal'a
still following that best practice of using as many functional components as possible.
Des'in mmkn olduunca ok fonksiyonel bileen kullanmaya ilikin en iyi uygulamasn halen takip ederek.
So here, this will be the cockpit constant which is just an arrow function where we simply returns some jsx
Yani burada bu, sadece IMJ'yi X olarak dndren sadece bir hava arac fonksiyonu olan
maybe, though there I will probably need more logic due to this the styling of the button, so we can return
kokpit sabiti olacaktr. Belki de orada olacaklar. Ben normalde daha fazla manta ihtiya duyacaz. U2, dmenin ekillendiricisidir;
a normal function body inside of which we returned our jsx.
bylece normal fonksiyon gvdesi iinde dnebiliriz GSX'e geri dnyoruz.
We will also receive props here
Ayrca sahne alacaz.
and as always, we need to import react from react to be able to really render jsx
Ve her zamanki gibi, GSX'i gerekten oluturabilmek iin reak' tepki vermemiz gerekiyor.
and finally, we will export our cockpit as the default.
Ve nihayet, varsaylan olarak kokpite ihra edeceiz.
Now what should go in there?
imdi ne girmeliyiz.
Let's go back to that app.js file,
O AP-Reals dosyasna geri dnelim.
I already mentioned it's basically this jsx code which should go into our cockpit.
Daha nce de belirttiim gibi, disk J, X kodu olarak bizim kokpite girmelidir.
So let's cut it here and let's move it into this return statement here in the cockpit,
imdi burada keselim ve burada kokpite disinterred ifadesine geelim.
now as you see, this of course throws an error because here we return multiple elements without a root
imdi grdnz gibi tabii ki bir hata atyor nk burada kk dm olmadan birden fazla e
node
dndryoruz.
and this is not supported here.
Ve bu burada desteklenmiyor.
Now we will dive into ways of supporting this in the next lectures,
imdi bunu bir sonraki derslerde destekleyecek ekilde dalacaz.
For now, let's simply wrap it into a div
imdilik onu bir lm haline getirelim.
but again we will find our ways of not having to use this div of over the next lectures because react
Ancak yine de sonraki derslerde bu gn kullanmak zorunda kalmamak iin yollarmz bulacaz, nk 16 numaral
16 offer us alternatives.
yasa deiiklii bize alternatifler sunuyor.
By the way we already see one alternative in persons, there
Bu arada, oradaki alternatif farkl insanlar var zaten gryoruz.
we return a list and of course this means that we have multiple person object sitting next to each other.,
Bir liste dndryoruz ve tabii ki bu, her saatin yannda oturan birden ok kii nesnemiz olduu anlamna geliyor.
there is no wrapping div.
Fark sarma yoktur.
But this is okay for react 16, this is a feature which is supported if you return a list, that is ok, you
gnlk bir liste dndrd takdirde desteklenen bir zelliktir. Tamam, birbirinin yanndaki eleri zorla kodlamayabilirsiniz.
just may not hard code elements next to each other.
Ancak bu yeniden hareket iin 16
So we'll fix this too in the next lecture
Bu yzden bunu bir sonraki derste de dzelteceiz.
but for now let's go with that,
Ama imdilik bununla balayalm.
and of course, we got these assigned classes thing you're in the cockpit where we manage the css classes
Ve elbette, bu atanm snflar, paragraflarn olmas gereken snflar olarak ynettiimiz kokpite girdiinize
the paragraphs should have
gre var ettik.
and the css class this button should have. We get the code for this in the app.js
Ve snf olarak grmek iin bu dmenin bir Disney-ABC kodunu almalyz.
file,
Dmek.
there
Orada.
we now need to grab the code, like const assigned classes where we take the persons length into account.
imdi, Konst gibi kodun, kiinin Lange'lerini hesaba kattmz snflar atmas gerekiyor.
Let's cut it from app.js and move it into our cockpit function here,
Aslnda evet olarak keselim ve burada bizim kokpit fonksiyonumuza tayalm.
there we of course access the state and this won't work.
Elbette devlete eriiyoruz ve bu ie yarayacak.
So we should expect to get persons as props on our cockpit element, now classes here needs to be imported,
Bu nedenle, kiileri kokpit elemanmza almasn ve imdi Colossus ylnn ithal edilmesini beklemeliyiz.
so we need a cockpit.css file
Demek ki bir kokpit kaps C-s var.
and in there, I will simply store the classes I'm using, red, bold and my app button classes here.
Ve burada, san ve cvatalar kullanan snflar ve uygulama dmesi snflarm burada saklayacam.
I will move them into the cockpit
Onlar kokpite gtreceim.
but this app class here no longer is correct
Ancak bu uygulama classier artk doru deil.
instead this should be cockpit probably because we no longer will nest this below this app class, the
Bunun yerine kokpit olmal nk muhtemelen Nesta'nn bu uygulama Clauss'un altnda uygulama
app class belongs to the app container and due to component scoping,
snf uygulama kapsaycsna ve bileen kapsamna bal.
if we were to reference app you're in a different component, this would not be the same automatically
Bavuruyu referans alacak olsaydk, farkl bir bileendeydiniz, ayn olmayacakt, otomatik olarak benzersiz
created unique identifier so it wouldn't work,
bir tanmlayc oluturuldu, bu da almazd.
we need to create a custom class for this component which we use.
Kullandmz bu bileen iin zel bir snf oluturmamz gerekiyor.
So with that we get the css classes added here,
Bylece c'yi buradan eklenen snflar olarak alyoruz.
we of course need to add that import to the file too.
Elbette o ithalat Faltu'ya eklemeliyiz.
So import classes from ./cockpit.css
Bylece noktal eik havuz kokpitinin CSX'inden snflar ie aktarn.
and with that, we can use classes here again.
Ve bununla birlikte snflar tekrar burada kullanabiliriz.
We also should create a root class here, class name which can be classes.cockpit
Ayrca burada Colossus Daut kokpiti olabilecek bir kk snf oluturmalyz.
and with that we should get scoping of our classes in the cockpit component again.
Ve bununla birlikte kokpit bileenindeki snflarmzn kapsamn tekrar belirlemeliyiz.
We still need to set up this button class here,
Hl bu dme snfn burada kurmamz gerekiyor.
so back in the app.js file here, we're switching button class conditionally depending on whether we show persons
Sonrasnda geriye dme snfn koullu olarak deitirip, ahsnza gsterip gstermemize bal olarak bu
or not. We'll have to put this logic into our cockpit component and also put the declaration of the button
mant kokpit bileenimize koymalyz ve ayrca dme snfnn bildirimini buraya
class there,
koymalyz.
so let's remove it from the app.js file and let's move it in there.
O halde dosyay asl evrak dosyasndan karalm ve ieride tanalm.
Here I will store my red class assignment temporarily and set up a class to be empty at the beginning.
Burada ret snf devimi geici olarak saklayacam ve balangta bo kalacak ekilde snfta ayarlayacam.
Now this will become important again for switching or for adding this red class to the button and
imdi bu, bir anahtarlama iin veya gn saysn dip sona okumak ve uygun stil
setting the appropriate styling.
ayarn yapmak iin tekrar nem kazanacaktr.
Now with that, we have to add this check where ever we want to add the red class to the button. So we can simply
imdi eklemek zorunda olduumuz ey Duret snfn dmeye eklemek isteyip istemediimize bir gz atalm,
do this by checking if props
bylece sahne kontrol ederek bunu yapabiliriz.
and then we should expect to get this show persons information.
Ve o zaman bu ov kiisinin bilgilerini almamz beklenmelidir.
So if props.showPerson, if that's the case then we should execute this class or add this class basically,
yleyse sahne ovu kiiyi gsteriyorsa, o zaman bu snf idam etmeliyiz veya bu snfta temel olarak
set this class.
bu snfa koymalyz.
So now if we analyze this, we expect to get properties defining whether we're showing persons and the
imdi bunu analiz edersek, kiileri ve kiileri gsterip tantmadmz belirleyen zellikleri elde
persons.
etmeyi umuyoruz.
Maybe we could even just get the persons length but that's totally up to you
Belki de sadece kiinin uzunluunu alabiliriz, ancak bu tamamen size kalm.
so for now I will simply go with the whole person's array which I expect. We should implement a cockpit
imdilik sadece btn insanlarn bulunduu aere ile gideceim, aslnda beklediim ey, aslnda evet
component in the app.js file appropriately, so in app.js which got a lot leaner,
dosyasnda bir kokpit bileeni uygulamak gerektiidir. Bu yzden ok daha temiz olan hisselerde.
we now want to use our cockpit component cockpit. For that
imdi bunun iin kokpit bileen kokpitimizi kullanmak istiyoruz.
first of all we need to add the import,
Her eyden nce ithalat eklemek gerekiyor.
So let's quickly do that. Let's import Cockpit with a capital C as for all custom components from the
bir ekilde, bileen klasrndeki tm zel bileenlere kyasla, bir ktleyle C ithal kokpiti alalm.
components folder
Bu yzden, hzl
and there from the cockpit subfolder and from the cockpit.js file without the file extension
Ve orada kokpit alt klasrnden ve dosya uzants olmayan kokpit Jarius dosyasndan.
as always. Now we can use cockpit and we're doing so down here and now I mentioned we expect two props
Her zamanki gibi imdi kokpiti kullanabiliriz ve burada bunu yapyoruz ve imdi Propst'in kiileri
there, showPersons is one and this should simply be this.state.showpersons and the other one is the
bir olarak gstermesini beklediimizden bahsettik ve bu sadece kiilerin gsteri ahsiyeti olmal ve dieri de ahsn
persons array itself,
kendisi olmaldr.
let me split this over multiple lines to make it easier to read, the persons properties should be this.
Beni birden fazla satra ble edelim ki kiilerin okumasn kolaylatrmak iin bu
state.persons.
devlet kii niteliklerine sahip olmaldr.
Now with that, we got a clearly focused app.js file with the cockpit and our persons array, we can
d var ve ahslarmz, bu sarmalamay kiinin dizisinin etrafnda kaldrarak biraz daha temizleyebilecekler.
now even clean it up a bit more by removing this wrapping div around the persons array,
imdi onunla aka odaklanm bir kokpitin bulunduu
wee don't need that,
Borca ihtiyacmz yok.
we can just return persons like this,
Bunun gibi insanlar geri getiremeyiz.
it's one component which renders the list,
Listede kalan tek bileen bu.
so we clean this up even a bit more.
Bu yzden daha fazlasn temizleyelim.
And beyond that we only get our handlers, our functions here which manipulate the state and that's exactly
Ve bunun tesinde, yalnzca ileyicilerimize devletimizi ileyen grevlerimizi sunuyoruz ve bu byle bir
the idea behind such a container.
kabn tam arkasndaki fikir.
It matches the state, it manipulates the state. Make sure all files are saved
Devletin tm dosyalarn kaydedildiinden emin olduklar durumu ynetir.
and let's now see if this still works.
imdi de ie yarayp yaramayacana bakalm.
If we reload, we got the toggle persons button
Yeniden yklersek, bir ahs dmesi konumalyz.
but it's not working.
Ama ie yaramyor.
I know why
imdi nedenini biliyorum.
because one prop was forgotten, when we click this button, onClick, we try to execute this.togglePersons
Tklamayla bu dmeyi tkladnzda bir pervane unutulduundan, ilk ileyicinin bu konumasn
Handler.
yrtmeye alyoruz.
This of course doesn't work, we don't have this method here,
Elbette bu ie yaramyor, burada bu yntemi kullanmyoruz.
we're not in a class here, we're in a function.
Burada bir snf deiliz, fonksiyonda.
So here we probably want to execute props clicked and then in our app.js file on our cockpit component
Dolaysyla, muhtemelen tkanan kollar altrmak istiyoruz ve daha sonra diyaframmzda kokpite den bileenimiz, bulduumuz bu uygun
we want to provide this prop clicked which we just defined and there execute togglePersonsHandler.
toplama ilemini yapmak istiyor ve bir kiinin ileyicisini Torg altrmak istiyoruz.
Now with that, we should have working button again and we do, we can toggle this, you see it gets the
imdi onunla tekrar bir krlma desenine sahip olmalyz ve bunun doru ekillendirmeyi grdn ve
right styling and everything works ask before
daha nce her eyin ie yaradn grdnzde kaydedemiyoruz.
but now we get a much better structure
Ama imdi ok daha iyi bir yapya sahibiz.
with clearly focused components and this is actually how you should compose and create your react
Aka odaklanm bileenlere sahibiz ve aslnda, yeniden uygulama uygulamanz oluturup
application.
oluturmanz gerekiyor.
You should have clear responsibilities of your components, have them narrowly focused, create granular
sorumluluklar olmaldr ve dar bir ekilde odaklanarak ayrntl bileenleri oluturmalsnz.
components,
Bileenlerinizin ak
use as many functional components as possible and have your containers be as lean as possible
Mmkn olduunca ok sayda fonksiyonel bileen kullann ve kutularnz olabildiince temiz tutun.
when it comes to jsx and styling, some containers may not even have a style file because they only
Dahas X ve stil sz konusu olduunda, baz kaplarn stilleri olmayabilir, nk yalnzca
import other components which then do the styling.
stil yapacak Abre bileenlerini ie aktarrlar.
So this is a very lean set up here which allows us to have a flexible and maintainable application.
Yani bu ok zayf bir balang ylym, bu da esnek ve bakml bir uygulamaya sahip olmamz salyor.